ANDREW LEACH



leach.andrew@gmail.com





Economist. Data Scientist. Policy Analyst. Academic leader. Author.

I am an energy and environmental economist and Professor of Economics and Law at the University of Alberta. My research spans climate, energy and environmental economics and policy with a focus on climate change policies and the law. I have advised federal and provincial governments and provided policy analysis to public- and private-sector clients. I am also an avid data scientist, exploring ways to summarize and visualize energy and economic indicators. I am a prolific writer, with over 200 bylines in major Canadian outlets.

EXPERIENCE

2006 - present University of Alberta, Tenure-Track Faculty Member

Professor, Faculty of Arts (Economics) and Faculty of Law (2022 - present)

Professor, Alberta School of Business (2022)

Associate Professor, Alberta School of Business (2011 - 2022)

Enbridge Professor of Energy Policy, Alberta School of Business (2012 - 2015)

Assistant Professor, Alberta School of Business (2006 - 2011)

2006 – present **Economics and Policy Consultant**

Environmental policy development and evaluation. Policy advisor to federal and provincial

governments. Expert witness on energy, economic, and regulatory files.

2015 Government of Alberta, Chair, Climate Leadership Panel

2012 - 2013 Environment and Climate Change Canada, Visiting Scholar

2003 - 2006 HEC Montréal, Tenure-Track Faculty Member

Assistant Professor/Professeur Adjoint, Institute of Applied Economics (2003 - 2006)

EDUCATION

2019 - 2020 University of Alberta LLM (Constitutional Law)

Thesis examined the constitutional anchors for climate change policies under the POGG, Trade

and Commerce, and Criminal Law powers of the federal government.

1999 – 2003 Queen's University Ph.D. (Economics)

Thesis applied numerical methods to examine the economics of climate change policy, including

distributional issues and the impacts of uncertainty and learning on optimal policy.

1998 – 1999 University of Guelph MA (Economics)

Focus on environmental, resource, and labour economics.

1994 – 1998 University of Guelph B.Sc. (Environmental Science)

Major: Environmental Economics and Policy.

WORK PRODUCT

Publications Academic Publications aleach.ca/publications

Data Data and visualization project archive aleach.ca/projects

Visualization

Opinion Opinion Archive aleach.ca/opinion

LANGUAGES HOBBIES NON PROFIT

English: native I am an avid cyclist, occasional runner,

French: proficient downhill and cross-country skier, hockey

player, and hobbyist woodworker.

Board of Directors, REACH Edmonton and Edmonton Juventus Cycling Club. Past Board Member, River Valley Alliance and Economic Society of Northern Alberta.